On December 7, 1941, at 7:55 AM, the first of two waves of aircraft from
Japanese warships launched from six aircraft carriers attacked Pearl Harbor, taking the
American forces. Although the attack resulted in the destruction of only
29 Japanese planes, 2,400 American sailors and soldiers died
and another 1,200 were injured. More than half of the military aircraft were
damaged or destroyed, most of which were on land at the time.
A day later, on December 8, the Japanese began their invasion of the Philippines and the
American and Filipino forces finally surrendered in May 1942. More than 2 years later,
In October 1944, American forces began the mission to recapture the Philippines from
Japanese troops led by the Military Governor whose units committed atrocities
unspeakable both there and on the island of Singapore. His name is Tomoyuki Yamashita.
Tomoyuki Yamashita, the second son of a local doctor, was born on November 8,
1885 in a town called Osugi, located on the island of Shikoku. In November 1905,
At the age of 20, Yamashita graduated from the 18th class of the
Imperial Japanese Army Academy. He was ranked 16th out of 920 cadets.
World War I began on July 28, 1914. During the war, Yamashita fought against
the German Empire in Shandong, China, and in 1916 he was promoted to captain. That same year he married
the daughter of a retired general and became an expert on the Germanic country, serving as
assistant military attaché in Bern and Berlin from 1919 to 1922. He then returned to Japan, but
after falling from grace as a result of his involvement with political factions within the
Japanese army, from 1927 to 1930, Yamashita was posted as a military attaché in Vienna, Austria.
After the Incident of February 26, 1936,
There was an attempted coup d'état in the Empire of Japan organized by
a group of young officers of the Imperial Army. Their goal was to purge the government
and the military leadership of their factional rivals and ideological opponents.
With this, Yamashita fell into disgrace before Emperor Hirohito after his plea for clemency.
towards the rebel officers involved in the coup attempt. He was eventually assigned to a
post in Korea and a year later, in November 1937, he was promoted to lieutenant general.
At that time, Japan was at war with China. Japanese territorial expansion
In East Asia it began in 1931 with the invasion of Manchuria and continued in 1937
with a brutal attack on China. Yamashita insisted that Japan should put an end
to the conflict with China and maintain peaceful relations with the United States and Great Britain,
but was ignored and subsequently assigned to a minor post.
Between 1938 and 1940, Yamashita was assigned command of the Infantry Division,
who participated in some actions in the north of
China against insurgents fighting the occupying Japanese troops.
World War II began on September 1, 1939, when Nazi Germany
invaded Poland. On September 27, 1940, Japan signed the Tripartite Pact with Germany
and Italy, thus entering the military alliance known as the "Axis". In December 1940,
Yamashita was sent on a six-month clandestine military mission to Germany and Italy.
Weeks after arriving in Germany, Yamashita was introduced to Adolf Hitler. While Hitler
He was trying to pressure the Japanese army to declare war on Great Britain and the United States.
United, Yamashita, facing the wrath of Russia and the continuing costs of Japan's war on
China showed no interest in this. Instead, it hoped to inspect the military techniques of
Germany and improve Japan's war prospects. Privately, Yamashita was disappointed
with the Führer. He told his staff: "He can be a great speaker from a platform,
But behind his desk listening, he looks much more like an office worker."
On November 6, 1941, Yamashita assumed command of the 25th Division Army, with which he
On December 8, he launched an invasion of Malaysia from bases in French Indochina. Due to
that the Japanese force was about one-third the size of the British forces in
Malaysia and Singapore, Yamashita commented that only a "determined charge" would ensure victory in
Malaysia. The plan was to conquer Malaysia and Singapore in the shortest possible time to overcome any
numerical disadvantage, as well as minimizing the possible losses of a prolonged battle.
The Malayan campaign concluded with the fall of Singapore on 15 February 1942,
in which Yamashita's 30,000 front-line troops captured 80,000 British troops,
Indian and Australian. This was the largest surrender of personnel led
by the British in history. After this victory, Yamashita became known as the
"Tiger of Malaysia." British Prime Minister Winston Churchill called the ignominious fall of
Singapore to Japan: the "worst disaster" and "biggest capitulation" in British military history.
The campaign and subsequent Japanese occupation of Singapore included war crimes committed
against Allied personnel and captive civilians. One of these massacres occurred at the Hospital
British Military of Alexandra in Singapore on February 14, 1942, around 1 p.m.
When the Japanese broke through the defenses and advanced toward the hospital,
who was trapped between the advancing Japanese troops and the forces
British in retreat. A British lieutenant, acting as an envoy with a white flag,
He approached the Japanese forces but was killed with a bayonet.
After Japanese troops entered the hospital, they killed up to 50 soldiers,
including some who were undergoing surgery. Doctors and
nurses. The next day, approximately 200 men, including staff and patients,
who had been gathered and tied up the day before, many of them wounded, were ordered to
walk about 400 meters to an industrial area. Those who fell along the way were stabbed.
with bayonets. The men were forced into a series of small rooms
Poorly ventilated cells, where they were kept overnight without water. Some died during the night.
as a result of his treatment and the rest were killed with bayonets the following day.
Several survivors were identified after the war,
some of whom had managed to survive by pretending to be dead.
Another massacre occurred on February 18, 1942, four days after the Japanese
officially conquered Singapore. The Imperial Japanese Army, with the help of the Kempeitai,
The Japanese secret police began a genocide against the Chinese population known as the Massacre
of Sook Ching. In Chinese, Sook Ching means "to cleanse by purification." The purge,
which was originally intended to last two days but stretched to over a week,
finally ended on March 4. Some experts estimate that between 10 and 20 percent of the
Chinese population in Singapore was killed during this massacre, which devastated the
general population. The death toll ranges from approximately 25,000 to 50,000 victims.
These atrocities were committed by soldiers under Yamashita's command.
On July 17, 1942, he was reassigned again from Singapore to Manchukuo,
a puppet state of the Empire of Japan in Manchuria from 1932 to 1945. It was given
a position in command of the First Area Army and was effectively sidelined for
much of the Pacific War. It is believed that General Hideki Tojo, who by then
He was the prime minister, and was responsible for his exile, taking advantage of Yamashita's mistake.
During a speech to Singaporean civilian leaders in early 1942,
when he referred to the local population as “citizens of the Empire of Japan.”
This was considered embarrassing to the Japanese government, which officially did not consider the
residents of the occupied territories had the rights or privileges of citizenship
Japanese. Despite this, in February 1943, Yamashita was promoted to full general
right. Some have suggested that he may have been sent there to prepare for an attack on the
Soviet Union in case Stalingrad fell to Germany. However, this never happened.
On September 26, 1944, when the war situation was critical for Japan,
Yamashita was rescued from his forced exile in China by the new government.
Japanese after the fall of Hideki Tojo and his cabinet. Thus, on October 10, the
command of the Fourteenth Area Army to defend the occupied Philippines. Yamashita
He commanded approximately 262,000 troops in three defensive groups.
He attempted to rebuild his army, but was forced to withdraw from Manila,
the capital of the Philippines, to the mountains. Yamashita ordered all troops,
except those responsible for ensuring security, will leave the city.
Soon, another massacre occurred.
In order to prevent the rescue of prisoners of war by the advancing Allies,
On December 14, 1944, near the city of Puerto Princesa in the Philippine province of
Palawan, units of the Japanese Fourteenth Area Army under the command of General
Yamashita took the prisoners of war back to their own camp.
After an air raid warning was issued for the prisoners
took refuge in the trenches, the 150 prisoners of war entered those
trenches and Japanese soldiers set them on fire using barrels of gasoline.
Prisoners who tried to escape the flames were shot dead.
by machine gun fire. Others tried to escape by climbing a cliff that was located along
along one side of the trenches, but were later hunted down and killed.
Only 11 men managed to escape the massacre and
139 were killed. This atrocity became known as the Palawan massacre.
While evacuating most of his soldiers, Yamashita, who also served as
Governor-General and Military Governor of the Philippines, did not declare Manila as a city
open. When a military commander or political leader formally declares an open city,
This means that the defending military forces will not defend the city in the
battle and the victorious forces can enter unopposed. The declaration of an open city
saves civilian lives and ensures that there is no destruction of buildings.
During the evacuation of Yamashita's soldiers,
Japanese Navy Admiral Sanji Iwabuchi reoccupied Manila with 16,000 sailors,
with the intention of destroying all port facilities and naval warehouses.
Once there, Iwabuchi took command of the Army's 3,750 security troops and, against
Yamashita's specific order turned the city into an open battlefield.
The battle and Japanese atrocities resulted in the deaths of over 100,000 Filipino civilians,
in what became known as the Manila massacre, during the intense street fighting for the
capital that took place between February 4 and March 3, 1945.
Yamashita managed to keep a part of Luzon, the largest and most populous island in the Philippines and
headquarters of the capital Manila, until after Japan's formal surrender in August 1945.
By the time of his surrender, his forces had been reduced to less than 50,000 due to
due to the lack of supplies and the harsh campaign carried out by elements of the forces
combined US and Filipino forces, including the well-known guerrillas.
Justice finally caught up with Yamashita when, from October 29 to December 7, 1945,
A US military tribunal in Manila tried him for war crimes related to
with the Manila massacre and many atrocities in the Philippines against civilians and prisoners of war.
For his part, Yamashita denied having any knowledge of the crimes committed by his men and
He stated that he would have punished them severely if he had had any idea that this was happening.
had happened under his command. He further argued that with an army as large as his,
There was no way he could control all the actions of all his subordinates. Therefore
So much so, he felt that what he was really being accused of was losing the war.
However, evidence that Yamashita had no final command responsibility
about all military units in the Philippines were not admitted to court,
who found him guilty of the charges and sentenced him to death.
Following the Supreme Court's decision, a clemency appeal was filed
to US President Harry S. Truman, who refused to intervene. Tomoyuki Yamashita
He was 60 years old when he was hanged on February 23, 1946, in the Prison Camp
of Los Baños, 30 miles south of Manila. The ruling against Yamashita set a precedent,
known as command responsibility or Yamashita standard,
in the sense that a commander can be held responsible
before the law for crimes committed by his troops even if he did not order them,
did not allow them to happen or if by chance he had no knowledge or means to stop them.
No tears were shed for Tomoyuki Yamashita.
Thanks for watching World History Channel don't forget to like and subscribe
and click on the notification bell so you don't miss out
our next videos thanks See you next time on the channel